Guide to the George Frederick Holmes Papers, 1767-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George Frederick Holmes papers 1767-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Holmes, George Frederick, 1820-1897.
3.6 linear feet Extent: 586 Items
Scholar, educator, and author of Charlottesville (Albemarle Co.), Virginia. Correspondence, notes, diaries, and literary works of George Frederick Holmes. Also contains correspondence of William Howard Perkinson, educator and son-in-law of Holmes; and of Joseph Henry Herndon Holmes and Mary Ann Pemberton Holmes, parents of George Frederick Holmes. Early papers of Joseph and Mary Holmes concern their life in Demerara, British Guyana, where Joseph Holmes was a barrister, and include legal papers, poems, and a genealogy. The papers of their son, George Frederick, a professor at the University of Virginia, include correspondence, diaries, articles, literary works, and notes, and relate to his interests in philology, grammar, history, political science and economics, and to Southern colleges and universities. The papers of William Howard Perkinson are confined to a few records of his work as a professor of Latin and Greek at the University of Virginia, a few business papers, and records of the administration of his father-in-law's estate.
RL.00564
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The George Frederick Holmes Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1948-1995.
Biographical Note
George Frederick Holmes was a University of Virginia faculty member, an early sociologist, and an ante-bellum writer who defended the institution of slavery. He fully described this position in his textbook, The Science of Society, published in 1883.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, notes, diaries, and literary works of George Frederick Holmes (1820-1897), scholar, educator, author; and correspondence of William Howard Perkinson (1861-1898), educator and son-in-law of Holmes; and of Joseph Henry Herndon Holmes (1794-1831) and Mary Ann (Pemberton) Holmes (1790-ca. 1862), father and mother of George Frederick Holmes. The papers of Joseph Henry Herndon Holmes, barrister of Demerara, British Guiana, consist of treatises on contracts and exchange of money, fragments of poetry, poems, his will, and pictures. Among the papers of Mary Ann (Pemberton) Holmes are the following: a brief record of her life in Demerara with interesting comments on the people and the country, family history and genealogy, personal letters, epitaphs, and verses of Stephen Pemberton written while attending Oriel College, Oxford, England.
The papers of George Frederick Holmes are chiefly concerned with family affairs, including financial troubles, and accounts from his wife, Eliza Lavalette (Floyd) Holmes, of the unsatisfactory performance of Negro servants; accounts of Holmes's connection with educational institutions, notably Richmond College, Virginia, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, the University of Mississippi, Oxford, and the University of Virginia, Charlottesville. The correspondence throws considerable light on dissensions in the Board of Visitors at the College of William and Mary in 1848. The collection consists of Holmes's correspondence with leading literary figures and educators of the South; notes and works on almost every phase of philology, grammar, history, political science, and economics; notes for lectures; articles and manuscripts for books and periodicals; lists of students; examination questions; and diaries which cover a great part of the period from 1856 to 1891. The collection includes a letter book, 1834-1874, containing contemporary copies of letters, in Holmes's hand, of many notable figures, among whom are E. E. Bellinger, Auguste Comte, J. D. B. DeBow, Thos. R. Dew, R. T. W. Duke, Wm. H. Ellet, Geo. Fitzhugh, John B. Floyd, Wm. Harper, R. R. Howison, R. W. Hughes, D. F. Jamison, Wm. S. Lewis, Francis Lieber, P. N. Lynch, Jno. McClintock, Cornelius Mathews, W. E. Martin, B. B. Minor, W. G. Minor, T. V. Moore, J. D. Munford, Edw. Nicholson, Wm. Ogilby, Cotesworth Pinckney, J. D. Pope, Wm. C. Preston, Jas. Ryder, W. G. Simms, R. W. Singleton, A. G. Summer, Jno. R. Thompson, Jas. H. Thornwell, Samuel Tyler, and D. K. Whitaker.
Papers of William Howard Perkinson are confined to a few records of his work as professor of Latin and Greek at the University of Virginia, a few business papers, and records of the administration of the estate of George Frederick Holmes. Some of Perkinson's letters to his wife give glimpses of the management of the university and of his work. M. Schele De Vere and W. Gordon McCabe, as well as a number of scholars in England, were among Perkinson's correspondents.
[Description taken from the Guide to the Cataloged Collections in the Manuscript Department of the William R. Perkins Library, Duke University (1980)]
Subject Headings
Holmes family; University of Virginia -- Faculty; Scholars -- Correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Southern States; Guyana -- Social life and customs
Contents of Collection
- George Frederick Holmes Papers, 1767-1960, (9 boxes)
  Box 7 also contains notes and correspondence by Mary Anne Holmes, Joseph H. H. Holmes, and Stephen Pemberton.
  - Papers
    - Sketch and genealogy (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and papers, 1815-1901 and undated (Box 1)
    - Works, 1845-1853 (Box 1)
    - Works, 1860-1876, 1880-1887 (Box 2)
    - Notes, 1885-1887 (Box 2)
    - Notes on political economy, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Works and papers on The Science of Society, 1889, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Works and papers, 1889-1891 and undated (Box 4)
    - Works and papers, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes, undated (Box 6)
    - Notebooks (Box 6)
    - Notes, undated (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
    - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Bound manuscript volumes
    - Diary, 1872 (Box 8, Volume S:1793)
    - Diary, 1873 (Box 8, Volume S:1794)
    - Diary, 1874 (Box 9, Volume S:1795)
    - Diary, 1881 (Box 9, Volume S:1796)
    - Diary, 1884 (Box 9, Volume S:1797)
    - Diary, 1885 (Box 9, Volume S:1798)
    - Diary, 1887 (Box 9, Volume S:1799)
    - Diary, 1891 (Box 9, Volume S:1800)
    - Articles for Biblical Cyclopedia I., 1878 (Box 8, Volume S:1783)
    - Articles for Biblical Cyclopedia II., 1878 (Box 8, Volume S:1784)
    - Excerpts regarding famous men, 1876 (Box 8, Volume S:1804)
    - Memoranda for Lives of the Governors of Virginia, 1853 (Richmond, VA) (Box 8, Volume S:1813)
    - Notes on Economics, 1892 (Box 8, Volume S:1814)
    - Notes on Greek History, undated (Box 8, Volume S:1818)
    - Notes on Oratory and Eloquence, 1878 (Box 8, Volume S:1820)
    - Notes on Oratory and Eloquence, 1878 (Box 8, Volume S:1821)
    - Notes on Oratory and Eloquence, 1878 (Box 8, Volume S:1822)
    - Notes on Oratory and Eloquence, University of Virginia, 1888 (Box 8, Volume S:1823)
    - "Population": a Crochet, 1887 (Box 8, Volume S:1824)
    - Notes on Rhetoric, University of Virginia, 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1825)
    - Notes on Shakespeare, undated (Box 8, Volume S:1826)
    - Notes on Sociology, 1892 (Box 8, Volume S:1827)
    - Notes for King Arthur and the Romances of the Round Table II., undated (Box 8, Volume S:1828)
    - "Notes on the Romances of the Round Table I.", 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1829)
    - "Notes on the Romances of the Round Table II.", 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1830)
    - "Notes on the Romances of the Round Table III", 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1831)
    - Notes of the Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1834)
    - Notes on the Social Sciences II, 1882 (Box 8, Volume S:1835)
    - Notes on Turkey, University of Virginia, 1878 (Box 9, Volume S:1841)
    - Songs and Poems, 1851-1879, 1912 (Volume M:1310)
    - Notes on British Guiana, 1823 (Demarara, British Guiana) (Volume F:1318)
    - Account Book, 1847-1857 (Richmond, VA) (Volume F:1781)
    - Adversaria: According to Locke's Method, 1840 (Columbia, SC) (Volume M:1782)
    - Class Rolls in Political Economy and History, University of Virginia, 1884-1894 (Volume L:1785)
    - Class Roll in Political Economy, University of Virginia, 1894-1897 (Volume L:1786)
    - Comments on Books and Authors, 1846-1850 (Richmond, VA) (Volume F:1787)
    - Comments on Books and Writers, 1846-1850 (Richmond, VA) (Volume F:1788)
    - Critical and Analytical Notices of Books, 1841 (Charleston, SC) (Volume F:1789)
    - Day Book, 1884-1894 (Volume F:1790)
    - Diary, Agricultural and War, 1856-1864 (Volume F:1791)
    - Diary, 1864-1865; also Miscellaneous Notes, 1841-1852 (Volume L:1792)
    - "An Elementary Grammar of the English Language for the use of Schools", 1867 (Volume L:1801)
    - Excerpts from Various Books, 1850 (Richmond, VA) (Volume F:1802)
    - Excerpts from Various Books, University of Virginia, 1852-1888 (Volume F:1803)
    - Historical Bibliographies, University of Virginia, 1890 (Volume L:1805)
    - Index Rerum, 1846 (Volume M:1806)
    - Inquiries on Various Subjects, 1841 (Walterboro, SC) (Volume M:1807)
    - Letterbook, 1835-1874 (Volume M:1808)
    - Lists of Students, University of Virginia, 1857-1871 (Volume L:1809)
    - List of Students in History and Literature, 1859-1871 (Volume M:1810)
    - Lists of Students, University of Virginia, 1871-1877 (Volume L:1811)
    - Lists of Students, University of Virginia, 1875-1884 (Volume L:1812)
    - Notes on English Language and Literature, University of Virginia, 1857-1860 (Volume M:1815)
    - Notes on English Language and Literature, University of Virginia, 1859 (Volume M:1816)
    - Notes on the English Language, University of Virginia, 1872 (Volume L:1817)
    - Notes on Law and History, 1845-1882 (Orangeburgh, SC and Charlottesville, VA) (Volume F:1819)
    - Notes on Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1857 (Volume M:1832)
    - Notes on Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1871 (Volume L:1833)
    - Notes of the Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1882 (Volume L:1836)
    - Notes on the Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1883 (Volume L:1837)
    - Notes of the Social Sciences, 1888 (Volume L:1838)
    - Notes on the Social Sciences, University of Virginia, 1894 (Volume L:1839)
    - Notes on Theology, 1845-1865 (Orangeburgh, SC) (Volume M:1840)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1840 (Decatur, GA) (Volume M:1842)
    - Articles, Public Addresses, and Occasional Comments, 1837-1857 (Orangeburg, SC) (Volume M:1843)
    - Science of Society, University of Virginia, 1882 (Volume L:2009)
    - Notebook, 1846 (Richmond, Henrico Co., VA) (Volume M:5959)